Guide to the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies Records, 1966-1982
University Archives Duke University
Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies records 1966-1982
Duke University. Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
3 Linear Feet
University Archives, Duke University.
Contains the records of the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, an interdisciplinary degree-granting program for scholars at Duke University. The Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies was established around 1968 in an effort to join and strengthen the medieval and renaissance programs at Duke University. Also includes materials of the Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies concerning the development of the program, the Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies. Types of materials include correspondence, budgets, newsletters, curriculum planning materials, announcements, reports, and minutes. Major subjects include the Duke University faculty, Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, university cooperation, renaissance study and teaching, and humanities study and teaching. Materials range in date from 1966 to 1982.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Transfer; 1978; 78-64.
Gift; 1989; 89-84.
Gift; 1992; 92-78.
Historical Note
The Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies was established at Duke University around 1968 after a committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies formed around 1966 to examine the possibilities of combining courses from a variety of disciplines. The committee analyzed faculty resources at Duke University and critiqued programs at other institutions. The committee then made recommendations to establish a Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, create a journal, provide undergraduate and graduate study programs, and establish a monograph series to permit publication of studies relating to the Renaissance and Middle Ages. Additionally, they recommended reviving the Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, active at Duke University from 1963 to 1969.
Each proposal was approved, and interdisciplinary coursework was planned for the 1968-1969 academic year under the guidance of the Medieval and Renaissance Studies Committee and the Duke Humanities Council. The distinguishing feature of the Program in Medieval and Renaissance Studies was the requirement of intensive work in the transmission of medieval texts. Degree-granting programs combined courses in fine arts, languages, history, and philosophy to achieve the goals of a well-rounded education in the humanities. The Center also sponsored or supported conferences, symposia, lecture series, meetings, and cooperative workshops with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Since 1971, the Center has produced the Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies (formerly titled Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies).
As of 2003, the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies has over forty faculty in ten different departments. All faculty participate in the University Program in Medieval and Renaissance Studies, which is the academic unit of the Center. The Center currently collaborates with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and North Carolina State University in the Joint Program for Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, newsletters, curriculum planning materials, budgets, announcements, reports, and minutes pertaining to the establishment and operation of the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies at Duke University. This collection reflects cooperative curriculum development among faculty of fine arts, sciences, literature, history, religion and philosophy departments. Materials range in date from 1966 to 1982.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Civilization, Medieval -- Study and teaching (Higher).
Duke University. Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies
Duke University -- Faculty -- History.
History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States.
Humanities -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Southern States
Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies
Renaissance -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina.
Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies.
University cooperation.
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Faculty -- History
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - General historical materials, ca. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Duke Humanities Council materials, ca. 1966-1972
  - Newsletters, 1970
  - Curriculum background materials, 1970-1971
  - Provost reports, budgets, minutes, agendas, 1974-1975
  - Medieval and Renaissance Studies Committee, 1970-1972
  - Lecture and events announcements, ca. 1968, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
  - Budgets and other financial materials, 1979-1980
  - Correspondence, course outlines, scheduled events, minutes, meeting notes, fellowships awarded, 1975-1980
Related Material
Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies Records.
University Archives, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Southeastern Renaissance Conference records.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Cooperative Program in the Humanities Report, [1963-1969] Call number: 378.73 C778R
University Archives, Duke University.